KAMAL RAJ LAMSAL, MA/LLB

Birendranagar 8 Surkhet, Karnali Province, Nepal

Mobile: +9779851169110

Email: kamal.lamsal@mu.edu.np

SUMMARY OF QUALIFICATIONS

With over a decade of experience as an Assistant Professor of Conflict and Peace Studies at Mid-West University, I have been deeply engaged in teaching, research, and public policy initiatives. My research primarily focuses on democracy, federalism, governance, human rights, and peacebuilding. I am actively involved in various research projects, including studies on the challenges of federalism and budget credibility in Karnali Province. I also lead a policy research institute and facilitate policy dialogues and capacity-building initiatives within Nepal's federal structure.

EDUCATION

- Summer University on Federalism, Decentralization, and Conflict Resolution
 Institute of Federalism, University of Fribourg, 2022
- Bachelor of Laws (LLB)

Tribhuvan University, Nepal (2014–2017)

- Master of Arts (MA) in Conflict, Peace, and Development Studies
 Tribhuvan University, Nepal (in collaboration with NMBU, Norway, and University of Ruhuna, Sri Lanka) (2007–2009)
- Bachelor of Arts (BA) in English Literature, Sociology, and Anthropology
 Tribhuvan University, Nepal (2003–2006)
- Proficiency Certificate Level (PCL) in Economics, English Literature, and Nepalese History,
 Culture, and Archaeology

Tribhuvan University, Nepal (2000–2002)

School Leaving Certificate (SLC)
 Government of Nepal, 2000

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Mid-West University, Surkhet, Nepal

Assistant Professor (Conflict and Peace Studies), March 2012 – Present

- Supervise master's students and mentor their research projects.
- Conduct and publish research on conflict resolution, governance, and peacebuilding.
- Coordinate curriculum development and act as Head of Department (2020–2023).

Serophero.com (Online Media)

Copy Editor, May 2017 - March 2020

Edited news content and wrote editorial pieces on governance, conflict, and public policy.

Government of Nepal, Ministry of Peace and Reconstruction, Local Peace Committee, Jumla Office Secretary (Peace Officer), October 2011 – March 2012

 Facilitated coordination among civil societies, political parties, and government agencies in postconflict settings.

Rajdhani National Daily

Sub-editor/Reporter, October 2009 – January 2011

Reported on foreign affairs and the peace process during Nepal's post-conflict transition.

PROFESSIONAL SKILLS

- Mediation and negotiation of disputes
- Capacity development in governance, human rights, and conflict management
- Facilitation of training on law, leadership, and youth empowerment

LANGUAGES

Nepali, English, Hindi, Tharu

LEADERSHIP AND AFFILIATIONS

- President, Hriti Foundation (Public Policy Think Tank, Karnali Province)
- Coordinator, Karnali Utsav: Kuda Karnalika (A Public Policy Festival)
- Head of Department, Conflict and Peace Studies, Mid-West University (2020–2023)
- Editorial Board Member, Nepali Journal of Social Research
- Advocate, Nepal Bar Council
- General Member, Federation of Nepali Journalists
- Life Member, Tribhuvan Community Library, Bardiya, Nepal

PUBLICATIONS

- Lamsal, K.R., "Role of Local Government to Combat Global Pandemic: A Case of Birendranagar Municipality," EROPA Conference 2022 (Unpublished).
- Lamsal, K.R., "Federalism as a Means of Political Participation of Minorities: A Study of Surkhet District in Nepal," IFF Working Paper No. 38, Fribourg, 2023.
- Lamsal, K.R., "Security Dynamics and Overhauling of Nepali Army," *Nepali Journal of Social Research*, 2022.
- Lamsal, K.R., "Conflict and Peace Studies in Nepal: A Need Assessment," *Nepali Journal of Social Research*, 2019.
- Lamsal, K.R., Ethnic Movements in Nepal: A Trend Analysis, Lambert Academic Publishing, 2012.

RESEARCH PROJECTS AND TRAINING

- Lead Researcher, "Province and Local Government's Budget Credibility in Karnali," Hriti Foundation & UNDP/EU Support to Inclusive Federalism.
- **Team Member**, "Challenges in Sub-National Governance: A Study of Karnali Province," Hriti Foundation, KUSOM Policy Lab, and GIZ Nepal.
- Team Leader, Capacity Development Plan for Local Levels in Karnali (Peace ERA Nepal Pvt. Ltd.).
- Facilitator, Policy Dialogue on Inclusive Federalism, Mid-West University Policy Lab.